Hello and welcome to another video where
we're going to learn about how to name
binary covealent molecules. Meaning that
whenever you have something that's
coalent that is all about sharing of
electrons between two different types of
non-metals.
So, with this naming scheme, it's
actually not uh too complicated of a
naming scheme. It's all regarding how
we're going to be putting down the
different types of prefixes. And then
we're going to really be trying to to
see how um we're going to be altering
all these different non-metals
uh using prefixes to show how many of
them are bonding together. So for
example, if we were to do uh the
following where I have N25,
how would I show the different prefix of
how this is bonding together? Well, it's
just simply just how we're counting and
writing all the different names. So the
first thing you're going to do is you're
going to be writing the first element
name and a prefix to say how many there
are. So we see the first species is
nitrogen. Okay. So, how many are bonding
to this? Well, if we look very closely,
we can see that there are there's a
prefix of two here. So, it's going to
tell you that all right, we're going to
use the prefix for two there. If we look
back up at our table up here at the top,
we'll see that. All right. Well, two is
referred to die. So, this is going to be
di nitrogen. Now, when we look at our
other species, well, it's going to be
very similar to ionic naming. We're
going to take the name drop only keep
the first syllable and replace the
ending with eyed. So we're going to do
this very similar thing. So being that
we have oxygen in our example. We have
oxen which is three syllables. We'll
keep the first syllable. So just ox. So
be oxide. Right? So if we have oxide
now we have a prefix of five.
So we're going to change that to penta.
So it's going to be pent oxide. And
whenever we have two vowels next to each
other, so a and o would have been next
to each other, we'll drop the one from
the prefix. So it be d nitrogen pent
oxide. All right, let's try another one.
Let's try a one that's maybe a little
bit more familiar to us. What if I do
something like CO2? Well, everybody here
is probably like, "Oh yeah, I know what
that one is. That's carbon dioxide."
Well, there you go. That's what exactly
this naming is based off of. But there's
one little little rule there, right? So
I have carbon, which is our beginning.
But notice how I did not use a prefix
or saying that there's one of them.
Well, whenever we have our first
element, we don't bother putting the
mono prefix for it. So it's just going
to be carbon. And then being that we
have two oxygens. So in this case, it
will be die. And then we'll do the same
thing as before. So it's going to be
carbon dioxide
will be the example that we'll use here.
So let's try a different one. What if I
do um C4
as an example? How do we do this one?
Well, same as before, right? We label
carbon out for the C. So that means we
start there. We don't put a mono cuz
it's the first element. There's only one
of them. Now we're going to do for the
next one which is chlor chlorine. We'll
keep the first syllable.
Drop the in part to make chloride.
So let's put that down. Now what prefix
am I going to use this time? Well, we
can see that we have a prefix of four.
So why don't we go up to our chart here?
And what we're going to see is that four
is tetra.
So we're going to end up altering that
and saying that it's going to be carbon
tetra chloride is going to be the name.
Okay. So we have our prefix
which tells you how many chlorines are
bonded to this carbon or in this
molecule. Uh if we try a different one.
Let's try
um let's try B2F6.
How would I do this one? Well, same
thing as before, right? We're going to
we got to look up our species, right?
You can see that's boron, but we can see
that there are two of them. So, what
we're going to do is die boron to show
that name. So, we do die as a prefix. We
write down our boron.
Now, we look see how many florines we
have and we can notice like all right,
there's six. So, which is six? Well, a
lot of these are going off the shape.
So, think pentagons, hexagons,
heptagons, octagons. So, hexagon. So a
sixsided
shape in this case. So this is going to
be dboron hexa
and then we have that florine. So which
becomes fluoride and that would be our
name. So this is the basics of how you
name different coalent molecules. So
this is how we do most binary species um
going through it. And then just to kind
of do another one more last example.
What if I just gave you the chemical
formula? Well, the best part is when you
get the chemical formula, you're just
reading what those different subscripts
are. So, if I see like, oh, well,
there's two nitrogens here. So, if you
remember, well, two was di
nitrogen.
And being that we have a single oxygen,
it would be monoxide. So, D nitrogen
monoxide.
And that would be our name. And how we
would name a binary coalent molecule.
This is a quick video from Dr. Dan.
Please come in for future videos and I
hope this helped. All right, have a
wonderful rest of your day. Bye.
[Music]